<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<lgr xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:lgr-1.0">
  <meta>
    <version comment="Second Level Reference LGR">3</version>
    <date>2024-10-25</date>
    <language>he</language>
    <unicode-version>11.0.0</unicode-version>
    <description type="text/html"><![CDATA[
       <div class="instructions">
<h2>INSTRUCTIONS</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>These instructions cover how to adopt an LGR based on this reference LGR for a given
    zone and how to prepare the file for deposit in the IANA Repository of IDN Practices.</li>
    <li>As described  the IANA procedure (https://www.iana.org/help/idn-repository-procedure) an 
    LGR MUST contain the following elements in its header:
      <ul style="list-style-type:square;">
        <li>Script or Language Designator (see below for guidance) </li>
        <li>Version Number (this must increase with each amendment to the LGR, even if the updates 
            are limited to the header itself) </li>
        <li>Effective Date (the date at which the policy becomes applicable in operational use) </li>
        <li>Registry Contact Details (contact name, email address, and/or phone number)</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>The following information is optional:
    <ul style="list-style-type:square;">
    <li>Document creation date</li>
    <li>Applicable Domain(s)</li>
    <li>Changes made to the Reference LGR before adopting</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>Please add or modify the following items in the <b>XML source code for this file</b> before 
  depositing the document in the IANA Repository. (https://www.iana.org/domains/idn-tables)</p>
<h3>Meta Data</h3>
<p>Note: version numbers start at 1. RFC 7940 recommends using simple integers. The version comment is optional, 
   please replace or delete the default comment. Version comments may be used by some tools as part of the page header.</p>
  <p><code>&lt;version comment=&quot;</code>[Please replace (or delete) the optional comment]<code>&quot;&gt;</code>[Please fill in version number, starting at 1]<code>&lt;/version&gt;</code></p>
  <p><code>&lt;date&gt;</code>[Please fill in with publication date, in YYYY-MM-DD format]<code>&lt;/date&gt;</code></p>
  <p><code>&lt;validity-start&gt;</code>[Please fill in effective date, in YYYY-MM-DD format]<code>&lt;/validity-start&gt;</code></p>
  <p>Note: the scope element may be repeated, so that the same document can serve for multiple domains.</p>
  <p><code>&lt;scope type=&quot;domain&quot;&gt;</code>[Please provide, in &quot;.domain&quot; format]<code>&lt;/scope&gt;</code></p>
<p><strong>Registry Contact Information:</strong></p>
  <p>Please fill in the <a href="#registry_contact_details">Registry Contact Details</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Change History</strong></p>
  <p>If you made technical modifications to the LGR, please summarize them in the <a href="#change_history">Change History</a> (and also note the details in the appropriate section of the description).</p>
<p>PLEASE DELETE THESE INSTRUCTIONS BEFORE DEPOSITING THE DOCUMENT</p></div>
       
       <section id="registry_contact_details">
<h2>Registry Contact Details</h2>
<ul style="list-style:none;">
<li><b>Contact Name:</b> [Please fill in Contact Name]</li>
<li><b>Email address:</b> [Please fill in Email address]</li>
<li><b>Phone Number:</b> [Please fill in optional Phone Number]</li>
</ul>
</section>
    
    <h1>Label Generation Rules for the Hebrew Language</h1>
 
    <h2>Overview</h2>

    <p>This document specifies a set of Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Hebrew language for the second level domain or domains identified above.
     The ultimate starting point for the development of this LGR can be found in the related Root Zone LGR [RZ-LGR-Hebr]. 
     Note that while it is the Hebrew Script Root Zone LGR that forms the starting point, the LGR defined here covers the Hebrew Language.
     The format of this file follows [RFC 7940].
     This LGR is adapted from the “Reference LGR for the Second Level for the Hebrew Language” [Ref-LGR-he-Hebr], for details, see <a href="#change_history">Change History</a> below.</p>

    <p>For details and additional background on the Hebrew script, see “Proposal for Hebrew Script Root Zone LGR”, Version 1.2, February 2019 [Proposal-Hebrew].</p>

    <p><b>Standalone LGR:</b> This LGR is designed to be used in a zone that does not cater to IDNs 
    other than those valid under this LGR. 
    This LGR lacks features that would allow its use in the context
    of another LGR in the same zone, and it may contain other features incompatible with such use.</p>

    <h2>Repertoire</h2>
    <p>The repertoire contains 27 code points for letters, 5 of which are variants (final forms) of 5 others. 
     The repertoire supports the Hebrew language with restrictions appropriate for domain names. 
     The repertoire is a subset of [Unicode 11.0.0]. For details, see Section 5, “Repertoire” in [Proposal-Hebrew].
        (The proposal cited has been adopted for the Hebrew script portion of the Root Zone LGR.)</p>
    
     <p>The Hebrew script is written from right to left. More details can be found in 
     Section 3, “Background About the Script and Languages Using it” in [Proposal-Hebrew].</p>

    <p>For the second level, the repertoire has been augmented with the ASCII digits, U+0030 to U+0039, plus U+002D HYPHEN-MINUS, for a total of 38 repertoire elements.</p>

       <p>Any code points outside the Hebrew Language repertoire that are targets for
     out-of-repertoire variants would be included here only if the variant is listed 
     in this file. In this case they are identified as a reflexive (identity) variant
     of type “out-of-repertoire-var”. Whether or not they are listed, they do not 
     form part of the repertoire.</p>

    <p><b>Repertoire Listing:</b> Each code point or range is tagged with the script or scripts with which the code point is used. For each repertoire element,
      one or more references document sufficient justification for inclusion in the repertoire; see the <a href="#ref_desc_sec_References">“References”</a> below.
      Comments provide additional information for some code points.</p>

    <h2>Variants</h2>
    <p>This LGR defines five in-script variants that are final forms of Hebrew letters. 
    For details, see Section 6, “Variants”, in “[Proposal-Hebrew]”.</p>

    <p><b>No ASCII Variants:</b> Note that this LGR does not contain
    definitions for “blocked” variants for letters that look indistinguishable from ASCII letters (homoglyphs).
    If concurrent use of LDH labels is desired, the resulting conflicts can be handled by using the “Common LGR” in processing. 
    For details, see Section 3, 
    “Use of Multiple Reference LGRs in the Same Zone” in [Level-2-Overview].
    </p>

    <p><b>Variant Disposition:</b> All variants are of type “blocked”, making labels that 
    differ only by these variants mutually exclusive: whichever label containing either of 
    these variants is chosen earlier would be delegated, while any other equivalent label should be blocked. There is no preference among these labels.</p>

    <p>This LGR does not define allocatable variants.</p>

    <p>The specification of variants in this LGR follows the guidelines in [RFC 8228].</p>

    <h2>Character Classes</h2>
    <p>This LGR does not define named character classes.</p>

    <h2>Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) and Context Rules</h2>
    <h3>Common Rules</h3>

    <p>By default, the LGR includes the rules and actions to implement the following restrictions mandated by the IDNA protocol. They are marked with &#x235F;.</p>
       <ul>
       <li><b>Hyphen Restrictions</b> &mdash; restrictions on the allowable placement of hyphens (no leading/ending hyphen
             and no hyphen in positions 3 and 4). These restrictions are described in Section 4.2.3.1 of RFC 5891 [150]. 
             They are implemented here as context rule on U+002D (-) HYPHEN-MINUS.</li>
          <li><b>Leading Combining Marks</b>   &mdash;  restrictions on the allowable placement of combining marks
             (no leading combining mark). This rule is described in Section 4.2.3.2 of RFC 5891 [150].</li>
       </ul>

    <h3>Right-To-Left Rules</h3>

    <ul>
        <li><b>leading-digit</b> &mdash;  restrictions on the allowable placement of digits in a right-to-left context (no leading digit), (see section 2.1 of RFC 5893 [160]); 
            implemented here as a context rule on each digit.</li>
    </ul>

    <h3>Default Actions</h3>

    <p>This LGR includes the default actions for LGRs as well as the action needed to
        invalidate labels with misplaced combining marks. They are marked with &#x235F;.
        For a description see [RFC 7940].</p>

    <h3>Hebrew-specific Rules</h3>
    <p>This LGR does not define rules specific to the Hebrew script.</p>
    
    <h2>Methodology and Contributors</h2>
    
    <p>The LGR in this document has been adapted from the corresponding Reference LGR for the Second Level. The Second Level Reference LGR for the Hebrew Language was developed by Michel Suignard and Asmus Freytag, based on the Root Zone LGR for the Hebrew 
       script and information contained or referenced therein; see [RZ-LGR-Hebr]. Suitable extensions for the second level have been applied according to the [Guidelines] and with community input. 
       As part of that process, features have been removed or modified as appropriate for the target language.
       The original proposal for a Root Zone LGR for the Hebrew script, that this LGR is based on, was developed by the Hebrew Generation Panel. 
       For more information on methodology and contributors to the underlying Root Zone LGR, see Sections 4 and 8 in [Proposal-Hebrew], as well as [RZ-LGR-Overview].</p>
    <p>[IL-IDN] was consulted during the work on this LGR.</p>

    <section id="change_history">
    <h3>Changes from Version Dated 22 April 2021</h3><p>Language tag has been updated.</p>

    <h3>Changes from Version Dated 18 May 2021</h3><p>Unicode Version has been updated.</p>

    <h3>Changes from Version Dated 25 October 2024</h3>
        <p>Adopted from the Second Level Reference LGR for the Hebrew Language [Ref-LGR-he-Hebr] without normative changes.</p>
    </section>

    <h2>References</h2> 
    <p>The following references are cited in the first part of this document:</p>
    <dl class="references">
    <dt>[Guidelines]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, “Guidelines for Developing Reference LGRs for the Second Level”, (Los Angeles, California: ICANN, 27 May 2020), https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/lgr-guidelines-second-level-27may20-en.pdf</dd> 

    <dt>[IL-IDN]</dt>
     <dd>Hebrew IDN Table for .IL 
     https://www.iana.org/domains/idn-tables/tables/il_he_1.0.html</dd> 
         
    <dt>[Level-2-Overview]</dt>
     <dd>Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers, (ICANN),“Reference Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Second Level: Overview and Summary” (PDF), 
     (Los Angeles, California: ICANN, 25 October 2024), https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/level2-lgr-overview-summary-25oct24-en.pdf
      </dd>     
    <dt>[Proposal-Hebrew]</dt> 
     <dd>Hebrew Generation Panel, “Proposal for a Hebrew Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)”, 24 April 2019, https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/proposal-hebrew-lgr-24apr19-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[RFC 7940]</dt>
     <dd>Davies, K. and A. Freytag, “Representing Label Generation Rulesets Using XML”, 
     RFC 7940, August 2016, https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7940</dd> 

     <dt>[RFC 8228]</dt>
      <dd>A. Freytag, “Guidance on Designing Label Generation Rulesets (LGRs) Supporting Variant Labels”, RFC 8228, August 2017,
    https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8228</dd>
    
     <dt>[RZ-LGR-Overview]</dt>
      <dd>Integration Panel, “Root Zone Label Generation Rules (RZ LGR-5): Overview and Summary”, 26 May 2022 (PDF), https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-overview-26may22-en.pdf</dd>

     <dt>[RZ-LGR-Hebr]</dt>
     <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Hebrew Script (und-Hebr), 26 May 2022 (XML)
      https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-hebrew-script-26may22-en.xml</dd>
     
      <dt>[Ref-LGR-he-Hebr]</dt>
      <dd>ICANN, Second Level Reference Label Generation Rules for the Hebrew Language (he-Hebr), 25 October 2024 (XML)
      https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/packages/lgr/lgr-second-level-hebrew-language-25oct24-en.xml
      non-normative HTML presentation: https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/packages/lgr/lgr-second-level-hebrew-language-25oct24-en.html</dd>

      <dt>[Unicode 11.0.0]</dt>
         <dd>The Unicode Consortium. The Unicode Standard, Version 11.0.0, (Mountain View, CA: The Unicode Consortium, 2018. ISBN 978-1-936213-19-1) 
     https://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode11.0.0/</dd>
     </dl>

    <p>For references consulted particularly in designing the repertoire for the Hebrew Language for the second level 
      please see details in the <a href="#table_of_references">Table of References</a> below.</p>

    <p>Reference [0]  refers to the Unicode Standard version in which the
      corresponding code points were initially encoded. References [101] and above correspond to sources
      given in [Proposal-Hebrew] justifying the inclusion of the corresponding code points or rules. Entries in the table may have
        multiple source reference values. 
        In the listing of <a href="#whole_label_evaluation_and_context_rules">whole label evaluation and context rules</a>,
        references [150] and [160] indicate the source for common rules.</p>

    ]]></description>
    <references>
      <reference id="0" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode Version 1.1">The Unicode Standard, Version 1.1/</reference>
      <reference id="101">Omniglot, Hebrew (עברית) https://omniglot.com/writing/hebrew.htm</reference>
      <reference id="150">RFC 5891, Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA): Protocol https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5891</reference>
      <reference id="160">RFC 5893, Right-to-Left Scripts for Internationalized Domain Names for Applications (IDNA) https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5893</reference>
    </references>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <char cp="002D" not-when="hyphen-minus-disallowed" tag="sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="HYPHEN-MINUS; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0030" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ZERO; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0031" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ONE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0032" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT TWO; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0033" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT THREE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0034" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FOUR; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0035" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FIVE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0036" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SIX; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0037" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SEVEN; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0038" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT EIGHT; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0039" not-when="leading-digit" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT NINE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="05D0" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D1" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D2" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D3" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D4" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D5" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D6" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D7" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D8" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05D9" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05DA" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Final form">
      <var cp="05DB" type="blocked" comment="Nominal form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05DB" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Nominal form">
      <var cp="05DA" type="blocked" comment="Final form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05DC" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05DD" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Final form">
      <var cp="05DE" type="blocked" comment="Nominal form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05DE" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Nominal form">
      <var cp="05DD" type="blocked" comment="Final form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05DF" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Final form">
      <var cp="05E0" type="blocked" comment="Nominal form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05E0" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Nominal form">
      <var cp="05DF" type="blocked" comment="Final form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05E1" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05E2" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05E3" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Final form">
      <var cp="05E4" type="blocked" comment="Nominal form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05E4" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Nominal form">
      <var cp="05E3" type="blocked" comment="Final form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05E5" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Final form">
      <var cp="05E6" type="blocked" comment="Nominal form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05E6" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" comment="Nominal form">
      <var cp="05E5" type="blocked" comment="Final form variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="05E7" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05E8" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05E9" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="05EA" tag="sc:Hebr" ref="0 101" />
  </data>
  <!--Rules section goes here-->
  <rules>
    <!--Character class definitions go here-->
    <!--Whole label evaluation and context rules go here-->
    <rule name="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of combining marks &#x235F;">
      <start />
      <union>
        <class property="gc:Mn" />
        <class property="gc:Mc" />
      </union>
    </rule>
    <rule name="hyphen-minus-disallowed" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of U+002D HYPHEN-MINUS &#x235F;">
      <choice>
        <rule comment="no leading hyphen">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no trailing hyphen">
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <end />
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no consecutive hyphens in third and fourth position in the label">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
            <any />
            <any />
            <char cp="002D" comment="hyphen-minus" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="leading-digit" ref="160" comment="RFC 5893 RTL labels cannot start with a digit &#x235F;">
      <look-behind>
        <start />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" match="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="labels with leading combining marks are invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="any variant label with a code point out of repertoire is invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="blocked" any-variant="blocked" comment="any variant label containing blocked variants is blocked &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="allocatable" all-variants="allocatable" comment="variant labels with all variants allocatable are allocatable &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="valid" comment="catch all (default action) &#x235F;" />
  </rules>
</lgr>